Register of the Herbert Hoover papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Herbert Hoover papers
1918-1978
62016
Hoover Institution Archives
169 manuscript boxes, 4 card file boxes, 2 oversize boxes (72.5 linear feet)
Writings, notes, typed copies of documents, printed matter, and financial records relating to American foreign policy and domestic policies during the presidential administration of Franklin D. Roosevelt, World War II, and the early postwar years. Consists mainly of drafts of and supporting materials for the posthumous book by Herbert Hoover, Freedom Betrayed: Herbert Hoover's Secret History of the Second World War and Its Aftermath (Stanford, 2011).
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1962.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1874 Born, West Branch, Iowa
1895 A.B., Stanford University
1914-1920 Chairman, Commission for Relief in Belgium
1917-1920 Administrator, United States Food Administration
1919-1923 Director, American Relief Administration
1921-1928 United States Secretary of Commerce
1929-1933 President of the United States
1939-1940 Founder, Finnish Relief Fund
1940-1942 Chairman, Committee on Food for the Small Democracies
1946 Chairman, President's Famine Emergency Committee
1947-1949 Chairman, Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government
1953-1955 Chairman, Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government
1964 Died, New York City
Scope and Content of Collection
The main body of Herbert Hoover papers is in the Herbert Hoover Presidential Library in West Branch, Iowa. The Herbert Hoover Papers in the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace consist primarily of drafts of, and supporting research materials for, what Hoover referred to as his Magnum Opus, which was left unpublished at his death. Centrally this was to be a critique of American foreign policy during the presidential administrations of Franklin D. Roosevelt and Harry S. Truman. However Hoover also intended to provide a critique of New Deal domestic policies, to write about Communist infiltration into the Roosevelt and Truman administrations, and to describe World War II relief efforts with which he was involved. His planned approach was in part objectively analytical and in part autobiographical. How to organize these varied themes, how to integrate the analytical and autobiographical approaches, and whether to attempt to fit everything into one work or into several, proved to be thorny problems with which Hoover grappled uncertainly over a lengthy period.
The successive drafts for the Magnum Opus make up the Unpublished Writings series, which is the heart of the collection. Hoover began writing while World War II was still in progress. The focus with which he began and to which he ultimately returned was on the diplomatic history of the war. Early drafts were referred to by his staff simply as the War Book. When tentative titles began to be assigned, each proved to be darker than the one before. "Lost Statesmanship" gave way to "The Ordeal of the American People" and it in turn to "Freedom Betrayed." Hoover's thesis was that Roosevelt had deliberately, deceptively and needlessly maneuvered the United States into the war, and that American participation and the war's outcome alike had been disastrous. This constituted a sharp dissent from the postwar triumphalist consensus in which Americans congratulated themselves on the victorious conclusion of a good fight in a righteous cause. For Hoover, on the contrary, the results of World War II were to be seen in its human and economic costs, in the extension of Communist rule over much of Europe and Asia, in the diminishment of America's moral stature with its complicity in this and with its use of atom bombs against civilians, and in the weakening of American democracy at home with the growth of war-swollen governmental bureaucracy and executive usurpation of legislative powers.
Perhaps because of the disparity between popular perceptions and Hoover's own judgments, editing of the Magnum Opus proved to be unusually extensive and protracted and publication long postponed. The July 1961 version of what was then titled "The Ordeal of the American People" was designated by Hoover as the fourth edition but there had in fact been more than three earlier versions. Successive versions were dubbed the fifth through the tenth. Then came what was called the Z edition because it was hoped that it would be the last. It was not. Subsequent versions, of which four can be identified, were designated Z+H (the Z edition with further editing by Hoover). The last version is dated December 1964, two months after Hoover's death. It was evidently arranged by surviving associates and reverted to superseded texts in some places.
The War Book saw published form only in 2011 as Freedom Betrayed: Herbert Hoover's Secret History of the Second World War and Its Aftermath, edited and with an introduction by George H. Nash (Stanford: Hoover Institution Press). Volume I of the published work conforms to the September 1963 Z+H edition. As Nash explains in his introduction, for Volume II he adopted subsequent changes that appeared to have been finalized by Hoover. Volume III, which Hoover left in the least finished form, draws on sections of earlier versions not included in the September 1963 or subsequent editing processes.
The Unpublished Writings series includes other writings not represented in Freedom Betrayed, which Hoover had ultimately come to limit to wartime foreign policy. Foremost among these are his critiques of the domestic policies of Roosevelt's New Deal. Hoover characterized these as collectivist and as foreign to the American tradition. He found them to have affinities not only with socialism and communism but also with fascism. Publication of these writings is planned. Other writings dealing with Hoover's World War II relief efforts were published in somewhat different form in the fourth volume of his An American Epic (Chicago: Henry Regnery, 1964). There are also miscellaneous autobiographical writings.
Changing notions of how the Magnum Opus was to be organized made for problems in arrangement of the Unpublished Writings series. The approach adopted has been to treat each version as a discrete bibliographic item, even though each version typically includes material re-used from previous versions and may in itself constitute only a portion of an intended greater whole. These items are arranged chronologically, highlighting the temporal progress of the composition process. At some point Hoover's staff arranged a large portion of the various drafts in files numbered Magnum Opus 1, Magnum Opus 2, etc. These followed approximate, but not exact, chronological order, and did not include all drafts. The reader who wishes to reconstruct this filing sequence may do so by following the notations in square brackets at the ends of relevant entries. These take the form of [MO1], [MO2], etc.
The research materials upon which the Magnum Opus was based are to be found in four supporting series. The New Deal Subject File consists of material relating specifically to New Deal domestic policies. The Communist Subversion Subject File consists of material relating specifically to issues of Communist infiltration of the United States government. The World War II Subject File consists of material relating specifically to wartime diplomacy. The General Subject File is a catch-all for material not falling neatly into any of the three categories above. It deals primarily with postwar international relations and postwar American domestic policies, but includes some earlier material. In addition to printed and near-print source material, these series include typed copies made from such sources, notes and memoranda made by Hoover and his staff, a few letters, and some miscellaneous Magnum Opus draft passages categorized by subject and not readily assignable to larger Magnum Opus versions.
A small Correspondence series consists of letters to and from Hoover relating specifically to the composition and prospects for publication of the Magnum Opus.
The Published Writings series consists of printed copies of writings by Hoover available elsewhere and present here because Hoover referred to them in the course of composition of the Magnum Opus. Notable in this series are the page proofs of The Problems of Lasting Peace, which Hoover co-authored with Hugh Gibson in 1942.
There are also a small Oversize File of collected printed matter, a small Audiovisual File, and a series of Hoover's personal Financial Records.
United States--Foreign relations--1933-1945.; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1953.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.
- Published Writings, 1928-1958
  Scope and Contents note
  Galleys, page proofs, printed copies, and typed excerpts of writings by Herbert Hoover published during his lifetime
  - Republican Party Presidential nomination acceptance speech, Palo Alto, California, 1928 August 11 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Printed text
  - The State Papers and Other Public Writings of Herbert Hoover, 1934 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Typed excerpts
  - Addresses upon the American Road, 1933-1938 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Printed excerpts
  - "President Roosevelt's Foreign Policy," Liberty, 1939 April 15 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Printed copy
  - "Shall We Send Our Youth to War?" American Magazine, 1939 August (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Speech to young Republicans re invasion of Finland, San Francisco, California, 1939 November 30 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Typed copy
  - Speech to young Republicans re invasion of Finland, San Francisco, California, 1939 November 30 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    Typed copy of address as published in San Francisco Chronicle
  - Further Addresses upon the American Road, 1938-1940 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Addresses upon the American Road, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - The Problems of Lasting Peace (co-author with Hugh Gibson), 1942 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    Page proofs with handwritten corrections
  - "History's Greatest Murder Trial" (re prospective war crime trials; co-author with Hugh Gibson), This Week, 1943 August 29 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - "A New Way to Make Peace" (co-author with Hugh Gibson), This Week, 1943 November 7 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - "Some Additions to the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals,", 1945 March 25 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Addresses upon the American Road, 1945-1948, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Addresses upon the American Road, 1948-1950, 1951 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - The Memoirs of Herbert Hoover, 1951-1952
    - Typed excerpts (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Galleys of serialized Collier's excerpts (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Printed copies of serialized Collier's excerpts (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Addresses upon the American Road, 1950-1955 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "An Appraisal of the Changes in the Charter of the United Nations," in U.S. Congress. Senate. Committee on Foreign Relations, Review of the UN Charter, 1955 (Box-folder 3: 2-3)
    Drafts, galleys, and working materials
  - 1958 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    Printed excerpt
- Unpublished Writings, 1944-1964
  Drafts and page proofs of writings by Herbert Hoover unpublished during his lifetime
  - War Book, 1938-1950
    - 1944 version
      - Drafts [MO1] (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
      - Drafts [MO2] (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - 1945 version
      - Drafts [MO2] (Box-folder 3: 8)
      - Drafts [MO3] (Box-folder 4: 1-4)
    - 1946 version
      - Drafts [MO4] (Box-folder 4: 5)
      - Drafts [MO4] (contd.) (Box-folder 5: 1-4)
      - Drafts re postwar famine [MO8] (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - 1947 version
      - Drafts [MO5] (Box-folder 6: 1-3)
      - Page proofs
        - Preface [MO6] (Box-folder 6: 4)
        - 1938 [MO6] (Box-folder 6: 5)
        - 1939 [MO6] (Box-folder 6: 6)
        - 1940 [MO6] (Box-folder 6: 7)
        - 1941 [MO7] (Box-folder 6: 8)
        - 1942 [MO7] (Box-folder 7: 1)
        - 1943 [MO7] (Box-folder 7: 2)
        - 1944 [MO7] (Box-folder 7: 3)
        - 1945 (Box-folder 7: 4)
        - 1946 [MO7] (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - 1948 version, drafts [MO9] (Box-folder 7: 6-7)
    - 1948 version, drafts [MO9] (cont.) (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - 1949 version, drafts
      - 1938 [MO13] (Box-folder 8: 2)
      - 1938-1939 [MO14] (Box-folder 8: 3-4)
      - 1939 [MO12] (Box-folder 9: 1)
      - 1940 [MO15] (Box-folder 9: 2)
      - Japan, 1940 [MO15] (Box-folder 9: 3)
      - Japan, 1938-1941 [MO16] (Box-folder 9: 4)
      - Japan, 1938-1941 [MO16] (cont.) (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
      - 1941 [MO10] (Box-folder 10: 3-4)
      - 1942 [MO17] (Box-folder 10: 5)
      - Russia, 1942 [MO17] (Box-folder 10: 6)
      - 1943 [MO11] (Box-folder 11: 1-2)
      - Russia, 1944 [MO17] (Box-folder 11: 3)
      - China, 1945 [MO18] (Box-folder 11: 4)
      - Poland, 1945 [MO18] (Box-folder 11: 5)
      - 1945 [MO18] (Box-folder 12: 1-3)
    - 1950 version, page proofs
      - 1940 (Box-folder 12: 4)
      - 1941 (Box-folder 13: 1)
      - 1942 (Box-folder 13: 2)
      - 1943 (Box-folder 13: 3)
      - 1944 (Box-folder 13: 4)
      - 1945 (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - "Lost Statesmanship,", 1951-1961
    - 1951 version, draft of Chapter 42, "Two Gigantic Mistakes" [MO20] (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - 1953 version, "Period X: The Consequences of War"
      - Drafts [MO21] (Box-folder 14: 2-3)
      - Page proofs [MO21] (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - 1954 April version (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
      Page proofs with corrections [MO24]
    - 1954 October version (Box-folder 15: 3-4)
      Page proofs with corrections [MO25]
    - 1957 version
      - Page proofs with corrections
        - Chapters 1-12 [MO39] (Box-folder 16: 1)
        - Chapters 13-33 [MO40] (Box-folder 16: 2)
      - Corrected page proofs
        - Chapters 1-12 [MO39] (Box-folder 16: 3)
        - Chapters 13-33 [MO40] (Box-folder 17: 1)
      - Duplicate corrected page proofs
        - Chapters 1-12 [MO41] (Box-folder 17: 2)
        - Chapters 13-27 [MO41] (Box-folder 17: 3)
    - 1958 October version
      Drafts
      - Part I. "The Foreign Activities of President Franklin D. Roosevelt and Their Backgrounds" [MO42] (Box-folder 17: 5)
      - Part II. "Roosevelt Prior to October 1937" [MO42] (Box-folder 17: 6)
      - Part III. "My Survey and Appraisal of the Forces in Europe Making for Peace and War in the Year 1938" [MO42] (Box-folder 18: 1)
      - Part IV. "The American Scene" [MO42] (Box-folder 18: 2)
      - Part V. "The Final Steps to the Second World War" [MO42] (Box-folder 18: 3)
      - Part VI. "From the Outbreak of War on September 1, 1939 to the French Surrender of June 21, 1940" [MO42] (Box-folder 18: 4)
      - Part VII. "From the Presidential Election on November 5, 1940 to Hitler's Attack on Stalin on June 22, 1941" [MO43] (Box-folder 18: 5)
      - Part VIII. Untitled [MO43] (Box-folder 18: 6)
      - Part IX. Untitled [MO46] (Box-folder 18: 7)
    - 1958 December version
      - Part I. "Mr. Roosevelt's Foreign Activities, June 1932 to October 1937" [MO44] (Box-folder 19: 1)
      - Part II. "My Survey and Appraisal of the Forces in Europe Making for Peace and War in the Year 1938" [MO44] (Box-folder 19: 2)
      - Part III. "The American Scene" [MO44] (Box-folder 19: 3)
      - Part IV. "The Final Steps to the Second World War" [MO43] (Box-folder 19: 4)
      - Part V. "From the Outbreak of War on September 1, 1939 to the French Surrender on June 21, 1940" [MO44] (Box-folder 19: 5)
      - Part VI. "From the Defeat of France to the Presidential Election, July 1940 to November 1940" [MO44] (Box-folder 19: 6)
      - Part VII. "From the Presidential Election on November 5, 1940 to Hitler's Attack on Stalin on June 22, 1941" [MO43] (Box-folder 20: 1)
      - Unnumbered and untitled section on Japan [MO45] (Box-folder 20: 2)
      - Fragments [MO44] (Box-folder 20: 3)
      - Fragments on Japan [MO47] (Box-folder 20: 4)
    - 1959 version
      This version titled "Lost Statesmanship: The Ordeal of the American People."
      - Drafts
        - Part I. "Mr. Roosevelt's Foreign Activities, November 1932-November 1937" [MO49], [MO52], [MO53] (Box-folder 20: 5-7)
        - Part II. "My Survey and Appraisal of the Forces in Europe Making for Peace and War in the Year 1938" [MO49], [MO52], [MO53] (Box-folder 21: 1-3)
        - Part III. "Some Communist Afflictions of the United States" [MO49], [MO52], [MO54] (Box-folder 21: 4-6)
        - Part IV. "From Roosevelt's Abandonment of Isolation in 1937 to the Polish Guarantees, March 31, 1939" [MO49], [MO53] (Box-folder 21: 7)
        - Part IV. "From Roosevelt's Abandonment of Isolation in 1937 to the Polish Guarantees, March 31, 1939" [MO49], [MO53] (cont.) (Box-folder 22: 1)
        - Part V. "From the Polish Guarantees of March 31, 1939 to the Outbreak of War on September 1, 1939" [MO53] (Box-folder 22: 2)
        - Part VI. "From the Attacks of the Hitler-Stalin Alliance on Free Nations, September 1, 1939, to the Surrender of France, June 22, 1940" [MO49], [MO50], [MO54] (Box-folder 22: 3-5)
        - Part VII. "From the Surrender of France on June 22, 1940 to the American Presidential Election, November 1940" [MO50], [MO54] (Box-folder 22: 6-7)
        - Part VII. "From the Surrender of France on June 22, 1940 to the American Presidential Election, November 1940" [MO50], [MO54] (cont.) (Box-folder 23: 1-2)
        - Part IX. "Hitler's Attack on Stalin" [MO50], [MO54] (Box-folder 23: 3-4)
        - Part X. "The Last Chance for Peace" [MO50], [MO54] (Box-folder 23: 5-6)
        - Part XI. "American Activities on the Atlantic Front" [MO50], [MO54] (Box-folder 23: 7-8)
        - Part XII. "From the Total Economic Sanctions on Japan of July 25, 1941 to Pearl Harbor" [MO50], [MO54] (Box-folder 23: 9-10)
        - Fragments [MO48] (Box-folder 24: 1-3)
      - Page proofs
        - Parts I-III [MO51] (Box-folder 24: 4)
        - Parts IV-VI [MO51] (Box-folder 24: 5)
        - Parts VII-IX [MO51] (Box-folder 25: 1)
        - Parts X-XII [MO51] (Box-folder 25: 2)
    - 1961 January version
      - Drafts
        - Part I. Untitled [MO56], [MO58] (Box-folder 25: 3-4)
        - Part II. "The Journey: Forces in Motion in 1938" [MO56], [MO58] (Box-folder 25: 5-6)
        - Part III. "Some Communist Afflictions of the United States" [MO58] (Box-folder 25: 7)
        - Part IV. "American Statesmanship Gets Lost in the Foreign Thicket of Power Politics, 1937-1939" [MO56], [MO57], [MO58] (Box-folder 25: 8-10)
        - Part V. "The 150 Days from the Polish Guarantees, March 1939, to the Hitler-Stalin Alliance, August 1939" [MO56], [MO57], [MO58] (Box-folder 26: 1-3)
        - Part VI. "The Ten Months from the Hitler-Stalin Declaration of War to the Surrender of France, September 1, 1939 to June 22, 1940" [MO56], [MO57], [MO58] (Box-folder 26: 4-6)
        - Part VII. "The Eleven Months from the Surrender of France, June 22, 1940, to the Presidential Election, November 5, 1940" [MO56], [MO57], [MO58] (Box-folder 26: 7-9)
        - Part VIII. "The Ninety Days after Roosevelt's Election to a Third Term on November 5, 1940" [MO55], [MO57] (Box-folder 26: 10)
        - Part VIII. "The Ninety Days after Roosevelt's Election to a Third Term on November 5, 1940" [MO55], [MO57] (cont.) (Box-folder 27: 1)
      - Page proofs
        - Parts I-II [MO56] (Box-folder 27: 2)
        - Parts IV-VII [MO56] (Box-folder 27: 3)
    - Unknown versions (Box-folder 27: 4-5)
      Miscellaneous, duplicate, and reject drafts and fragments.
    - Unknown versions (cont.) (Box 28)
    - Unknown versions (cont.) (Box-folder 29: 1-2)
  - "The Years as Crusader," page proofs [MO19], 1951 (Box-folder 88: 1)
  - "The Four Horsemen in World War II,", 1951
    - Page proofs [MO19] (Box-folder 88: 2)
    - Partial page proofs for review by George Sokolsky [MO19] (Box-folder 88: 3)
  - "The Crusade Years,", 1953
    - Drafts [MO22] (Box-folder 88: 4-5)
    - Drafts [MO22] (cont.) (Box-folder 89: 1)
    - Page proofs [MO23] (Box-folder 89: 2-3)
  - "Some Notes on Family Life,", 1955 August (Box-folder 89: 4)
    Drafts [MO26]
  - "The Crusade against Famine in World War II"
    - 1955 August version (Box-folder 90: 1)
      Drafts [MO27]
    - 1955 November version
      - Drafts [MO29] (Box-folder 92: 3-4)
      - Drafts [MO29] (cont.) (Box-folder 93: 1-2)
      - Page proofs [MO30] (Box-folder 93: 3)
      - Page proofs [MO31] (Box-folder 93: 4)
  - "Crusading for Benevolent Institutions,", 1955 November (Box-folder 90: 2)
    Drafts [MO32]
  - "The Crusade against Collectivism in American Life,", 1955 November
    - Page proofs [MO33] (Box-folder 90: 3-4)
    - Page proofs with corrections [MO28] (Box-folder 91: 1-2)
    - Page proofs with corrections [MO34] (Box-folder 91: 3)
    - Page proofs with corrections [MO34] (cont.) (Box-folder 92: 1)
    - Page proofs with corrections (Box-folder 92: 2)
  - "Crusade against Waste in the Federal Government, 1921 to 1955," drafts [MO35], 1955 November (Box-folder 94: 1-2)
  - "The Crusade for American Children,", 1955 December
    - Drafts [MO38] (Box-folder 94: 3)
    - Page proofs [MO38] (Box-folder 94: 4)
  - "My Crusade against Collectivism,", 1955 December
    - Drafts [MO36] (Box-folder 94: 5)
    - Page proofs [MO36] (Box-folder 94: 6)
    - Page proofs [MO37] (Box-folder 94: 7)
  - "Forty-four Years Fight against Famine and Destitution,", 1958 (Box-folder 17: 4)
  - "The Ordeal of the American People"
    - Volume II, 1961 February version
      - Section A. "We Go from Pearl Harbor, December 7, 1941, to Tehran, November 28, 1943" [MO59] (Box-folder 29: 3)
      - Section K-1. "The Period from Tehran to Yalta" [MO59] (Box-folder 29: 4)
      - Section K-1 [sic]. "The Yalta Conference, February 4 to February 11, 1945" [MO59] (Box-folder 30: 1)
      - Section K-2. "The Period from Yalta to Potsdam, February-August 1945" [MO59] (Box-folder 30: 2)
    - 1961 May version, unnumbered section: "An Appraisal of the March of Communism Seven Months after the War's End
      - General (Box-folder 30: 3)
      - Chapter 60. "France, Italy, Switzerland, Belgium and Holland" (Box-folder 30: 4)
      - Chapter 61. "The Baltic Countries" (Box-folder 30: 5)
      - Chapter 62. "Germany, Poland and Czechoslovakia" (Box-folder 30: 6)
      - Chapter 63. "Austria, Hungary, Bulgaria, Albania, Yugoslavia, Rumania and Greece" (Box-folder 31: 1)
      - Chapter 64. "The Moslem and Christian Nations in the Middle East" (Box-folder 31: 2)
      - Chapter 65. "India, Thailand and the Philippines" (Box-folder 31: 3)
      - Chapter 66. "An Appraisal of the Progress of Communism in China, Korea, Japan and Russia" (Box-folder 31: 4)
      - Chapter 67. "The Epic of the Greatest Famine in Human History" (Box-folder 31: 5)
    - 4th edition, 1961 July
      - Section I. "The Infiltration of Communism in the United States" [MO63], [MO64] (Box-folder 31: 6-7)
      - Section II. "1938: Signs and Portents of War" [MO62], [MO63], [MO64] (Box-folder 31: 8)
      - Section II. "1938: Signs and Portents of War" [MO62], [MO63], [MO64] (cont.) (Box-folder 32: 1-3)